<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opinion | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T09:03:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to stock a bar]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2013/03/11/how-to-stock-a-bar/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-11T22:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2013/03/11/how-to-stock-a-bar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>
<p>As everyone that knows me knows, I have become enamored with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocktail">cocktails</a>.</p>

<p>So I thought, with that amazing hubris encapsulated within the novice, I would
tell you, the reader, how to stock a bar if you are new to cocktails yourself.</p>

<p>I’ll split this amateur’s amateur guide into the following sections:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The Equipment</li>
  <li>The Drink</li>
  <li>The Practice</li>
  <li>The Expansion</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="the-equipment">The Equipment</h1>

<p>I will start by listing the equipment you need. This will seem like a lot; but
you can find some of it in ‘kits’ which will help you get started (replacing
crappy items as you realize that there are better tools).</p>

<ul>
  <li>a jigger<sup id="fnref:jigger"><a href="#fn:jigger" class="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>a shaker set. (I prefer a Boston Shaker<sup id="fnref:bostonshaker"><a href="#fn:bostonshaker" class="footnote">2</a></sup>)</li>
  <li>a strainer (such as a Hawthorne Strainer<sup id="fnref:strainer"><a href="#fn:strainer" class="footnote">3</a></sup>)</li>
  <li>a bar spoon<sup id="fnref:barspoon"><a href="#fn:barspoon" class="footnote">4</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<p>This seems like a lot of stuff - but like I said you can find it in ‘kits’. If
you can get better tools from a specialty store (such as <a href="http://www.thebostonshaker.com/">The Boston Shaker</a>).</p>

<h1 id="the-drink">The Drink</h1>

<p>You should start with one or two drinks you like and that have only a few
ingredients. For example a Manhattan or Negroni only have 3 ingredients; a Gin
and Tonic only two (three if you count the lime). Pick drinks you really like
because you will be making them a lot.  It also helps if you pick drinks with
‘standard’ ingredients, like Gin, Vodka, Rye, Bourbon, Whisky, Campari etc.
This makes it easier to buy these ingredients from your local liquor store.</p>

<h1 id="the-practice">The Practice</h1>

<p>Now that you have the equipment and the ingredients; make yourself a drink –
you deserve it! Then make it again, and again, and again…</p>

<p>As you practice, you’ll figure out how to measure (and when you don’t care
about measuring), you’ll figure out how to stir or shake well, how much ice
you might need etc.</p>

<h1 id="the-expansion">The Expansion</h1>

<p>Once you have gotten good a drink (or perhaps sick of it) look for a drink
which has all the same ingredients but in different proportions; or a drink
that has a different ingredient you don’t have yet.</p>

<p>In this way your repertoire will grow and your skill will as well.</p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:jigger">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jigger_(unit)#Jigger <a href="#fnref:jigger" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:bostonshaker">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_shaker <a href="#fnref:bostonshaker" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:strainer">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocktail_strainer <a href="#fnref:strainer" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:barspoon">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bar_spoon <a href="#fnref:barspoon" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
