<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-13T10:13:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year Without a Office Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/04/08/a-year-without-a-office-desk/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-08T20:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/04/08/a-year-without-a-office-desk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Well not quite true I don’t have a desk at all… but effectively I don’t
have one).</p>

<p>About a year ago I changed to a new job. In all previous jobs I’ve had I had a
desk, in fact I had a office (sometimes shared) or at least a cube of my own.
It was different at the new job; when I showed up on my first day at the new
work there was a little bit of confusion about what cube I could be given and
as a ‘temporary’ solution I was given a desk in the lab.</p>

<p>Given the way we work on the team, I spent very little time at my desk. It
became simply a place where I put my bag &amp; coat; a place for my coffee mug; a
place for my notebook at the end of the day. I did use it to check my email
first thing in the morning before everyone arrived (I’m an early person) - but
other than that - unused. As the months went on I used it less and less
everyday.</p>

<p>Then in January the new DBA consultant started sitting at it with his laptop
so he could be with the team; thus I was partially evicted from my ‘desk’. I
still kept my inbox there - but now I didn’t even use the desk to read my
email in the morning.</p>

<p>At this same time there was a new coworker starting and with that a little
angst about where they would sit (the cube situation was in fact no better;
but actually worse). A cube was found for her; but I felt that by giving up my
desk entirely I was making a personal statement about desks, cubes, offices.</p>

<p>I do have regrets periodically when I need to do some personal matters; but we
have a shared office nearby the lab and a few cubes that can be used in a
pinch for private work/calls.</p>

<p>In all - I have not really missed having a desk. I have found out that I don’t
need much more than space for my inbox; maybe someday space for some filing.
This conclusion is NOT what I would have expected from myself; I remember
clearly wanting an office and bemoaning my fate of being in cubes. It seems I
have accepted the team-room setting more than I had imagined I could have.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Learned Agile All Wrong and Still Ended Up Liking it.]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/13/how-i-learned-agile-all-wrong-and-still-ended-up-liking-it/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-13T00:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/13/how-i-learned-agile-all-wrong-and-still-ended-up-liking-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="history">History</h2>

<p>Up until several years ago I only knew one way to do a software project.
The “usual” way: Requirements document; bunch of coding; deadlines which
were basically impossible; throwing the app at QA; thrashing to “improve
quality”; sending it to the customer and then “firefighting” to fix the
fact that it didn’t meet the requirements.  Sure there were glimpse of
other ways; small changes to the process etc.; but generally the same.</p>

<p>Then I learned about “Agile”. (I fully intend those quotes). The company
I worked for was bought by another larger company. That company seems to
have had a team which “went Agile” from the bottom up and the company
decided that it was going to be the “new way”. I was one of the
“important people” who was on the new project which was going to be one
of the flagship “Agile” projects.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-was-taught">What I Was Taught</h2>

<p>We got two(ish) days of consulting. We were taught story writing,
planning poker, iterations, QA in-iteration, and some TDD examples (damn
Bowling Game). The impression I <em>got</em> was that we’d be working in close
teams, prioritizing every iteration (because requirements are always
changing), working hard to produce only the code we need (and do it
cleanly), release this frequently to get quick feedback. I also was
“taught” the “don’t do design” idea.  I know several of my team members
feel they heard the same.</p>

<p>I thought this was <strong>AWESOME</strong>. I drank the Kool-Aid and then went back for
a second cup.</p>

<p>I worked to learn more and more. The company sent me to Agile2008, and I
I took myself to Agile2009. I went to other conferences, I read books,
blogs, I went to meetups and talked with people.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h2>

<p>I learned many things, sometimes the hard way, not all direct lessons.</p>

<p>I learned that “going Agile” isn’t going to work unless people want to
give it a try. Imposing “Agile” from above won’t work. The people
involved need to want to at least try it. Most important of course is
the by-in from management in and above the team.</p>

<p>I learned, and am still learning, ways to help teach and learn from my
coworkers. At first, being very gung-ho about it, I came off a bit too
“you’re doing it wrong!” and that turned people off and probably burned
a few bridges that could have been useful later.</p>

<p>I learned that having QA in-iteration, or even better, “pairing” with QA
on the tests (automated or manual) for a story is very powerful and can
flush out issues (potential or realized) quickly.</p>

<p>I learned that the “don’t design” idea doesn’t work. (I probably wasn’t
intentionally taught that, but I really feel that it came out during our
training. Perhaps an overemphasis on not getting attached to an up-front
design and letting TDD take its course.)  I initially tried it, while my
coworkers rejected it, and TDD, without trying it.  I think by trying -
and not succeeding - at it I have become better at what amount of design
is needed, and how TDD can lead to good designs (at least at the micro
level).</p>

<p>I learned that my ideas about OO design were not good. I was mostly
just doing imperative programming in big bags of loosely related things
I called <em>classes</em>.</p>

<p>I learned that clean code is flexible and can be easy to understand and
make changes to. I learned that I had a LOT more to learn about writing
clean code.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-like">What I Like</h2>

<p>I love the idea of transparency. This was not taught. I learned it own
my own and I feel it is one of the most important things about “Agile”
and wonder why it is not presented more.  It can be scary, very scary,
not to be able to hide behind the buffered schedule, or the layers of
management, but in the end I think it is better to be open and up-front
about everything going on in a project.  If there are problems it is
best to get them out in the open earlier, so that they can be addressed
earlier (when it is generally easier to address them).</p>

<p>I like working incrementally. Working on small stories in time-boxed
iterations help me to keep focused.  Each iteration I have to make sure
that we have a (at least potentially) releasable product. I learned long
ago that today’s new product is tomorrow’s maintenance product. So
bringing out the maintenance problems by practicing the release every
iteration brings out the maintenance problems sooner.</p>

<p>I like working with in-iteration QA. Being able to work with these
professionals closely helps me ensure my code does what it needs to do,
does what it should, and most importantly doesn’t do anything else. It
also gives me quick feedback.</p>

<p>I like quick feedback, always have (but I had forgotten over
time). Quick feedback helps me focus on what is needed and keep the aim
true. If the aim is off we know faster and adjustments can be made. Also
obviously easier to fix issues found sooner than later.</p>

<p>I love TDD. Plain and simple. It took me a little while, but after being
taught the TDD technique, I realized I knew it. I used to call that sort
of programming “exploratory”. When I had a REPL, I coded by trying
something out, testing, playing; then I’d save it and test the larger
chunk. This would be repeated. Without a REPL I’d do it in a larger
slower edit-compile-debug cycles.</p>

<p>Finally, I like how what I have learned has moved me to much produce
much cleaner code. I still have much to learn here. But the “stressors”
of repeated frequent releases, evolving requirements, and TDD have
pushed me to write, IMHO, much better code. It has also driven me to
think outside the imperative and OO paradigms.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-still-want-to-learn">What I Still Want to Learn</h2>

<p>I do still need to learn much more about producing the best code I
can. Also to keep in mind that the “best code” must also be the “right
code” - it must provide the features needed.</p>

<p>I still need to learn some “people” things. I need to learn how to
better learn from, and teach people.</p>

<p>And most importantly I have learned I need to learn much more.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Change your organization or change your organization]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/08/change-your-organization-or-change-your-organization/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-08T22:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/08/change-your-organization-or-change-your-organization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Several years ago I was pointed to Martin Fowler’s quote.
For the next few years I tried the first half of the quote. It was hard 
bit I didn’t really have much luck. Sometimes I felt like giving up; 
quitting or worse - going with the flow. I sometimes wanted to let the 
people and company do what it wanted and let the chips fall - at least I 
would be able to say “I told you so”.</p>

<p>Finally I decided to follow the second part of the quote; and that is 
what I’ve done. In some ways it feels a little like quitting or giving 
up. But trying to change the organization that doesn’t want to change is 
very tiring.</p>

<p>I hope that the new organization will be a better fit for me.</p>

<p>Fit. I think that is the key. The company <em>was</em> a good fit for me, but not 
any more. We no longer fit; and so since I cannot work to change them, 
I’ll do the changing.</p>

<p>Hope I’ll get over feeling like I’ve failed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Change is Scary]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/04/change-is-scary/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-04T22:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/04/change-is-scary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I did something that was hard for me - something I haven’t done 
for a decade - I quit my job and accepted another one. It hasn’t been a 
decade because my current job was so great, as people who I have talked 
with over the last couple years know, but because I was scared.
Change is not easy for me - especially change which seems big to me - 
like changing my job. I pay my mortgage with that paycheck after all, 
thus I put a lot of importance upon it, probably too much.</p>

<p>But now change is happening. My new position may not be my “dream job”, 
I don’t even know what that might be frankly, but I think it has a good 
chance of being a better job. I’ll be working with some great people 
and I am sure I’ll learn a lot.</p>

<p>I’ll be put in the position where people are going to expect I’ll know a 
lot of things - and I’m simply not going to. I’m going to try to deal 
with those situations, when they arise, without running away screaming.</p>

<p>This change has been long overdue, but I am finally taking it.</p>

<p>Here’s to change.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
