<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: viking | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/viking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T08:38:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Viking Boston Bike Ride: The Trip to Norumbega]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/05/07/viking-boston-bike-ride-the-trip-to-norumbega/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/05/07/viking-boston-bike-ride-the-trip-to-norumbega</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Norumbega is a mythical place, a sort of place holder name for unknown
locations in the New England area[1].  Today I biked there, battling
thunderstorms, mobs of Steampunk cosplayers[2], and mechanical failures[3], to
the dark, abandoned, closed tower which is the lonely outpost of the
area&rsquo;s long lost Viking past.</p>

<p>Eben Norton Horsford[4] held the Rumford Chair of the Application of
Science to the Useful Arts at Harvard in the late 1840&rsquo;s[5].  He later
founded the Rumford Chemical Works and produced an improved recipe for
baking powder. This baking powder is still being produced as <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/5696817133/in/set-72157626544381657">Rumford
Baking
Powder</a>.
He also held the controversial[6] idea that Lief Erikson[7] sailed up
the Charles River, as far as Waltham (near present day Brandeis
University) and ultimately building a house in Cambridge.</p>

<p>I decided that I would trace Leif&rsquo;s trip up Charles River, Gale would be
my longship and we&rsquo;d brave all trials and tribulations we might find
along the way.</p>

<p>The expedition started as all good expeditions do with a good
breakfast (in this case supplied by my lovely wife Wendy who cooked some
delicious pancakes[8]), and the laying in of supplies (16oz of
Clover&trade; brewed New Guinea coffee put into my thermos from the local
Starbucks).  With these preliminaries completed I started my fateful
trip.</p>

<p>Stopping first to contemplate the location of Lief Erikson&rsquo;s house.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3119/5696817467_2579529afb.jpg" alt="Location of Lief Erikson's House" /></p>

<p>It lay just outside the back of Mt. Auburn Hospital, I wondered just
what this spot must have looked like in the year 1000 BCE; probably less
traffic.</p>

<p>From there I started the long ride up the river to my next destination.
I had not before ridden so far up the river (usually just stopping at
Watertown dam).  I took several wrong turns because I didn&rsquo;t know how
the &ldquo;Blue Heron&rdquo;[9] path ran so I missed it in a few places; and worse
turned in the wrong direction entirely when part of it turned out to be
closed in Waltham.  The clouds were rolling in and so was the thunder, I
was worried that I was going to be caught in the rain and I had not yet
found the tower. Riding through Mt. Feake Cemetery the rain caught up
with me.  Through the cemetery quickly and then ducking into the
Brandeis-Roberts train stop I hoped to wait out the rain.  I sipped some
coffee and waited.  The rain continued but it looked like it was
brightening.  Checking my map I knew I was close to the tower.  I
decided that the rain was lightening up so I recounted for the final
stretch.</p>

<p>Mother Nature, that fickle woman, was up to her usual tricks and mere
moments later I was soaked as the rain quickly got worse.  I pressed on
to the tower and was pleasantly surprised to find it much easier to find
than expected.</p>

<p>The tower marks the location where there had been a Norse
fort/city[10] according to Horsford.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2756/5697394164_817d1d3379.jpg" alt="Norumbega
 Tower" /></p>

<p>At one point it seemed that the public could climb the inside of the
tower to enjoy the view from the top, but now it was all blocked off
with welded in gates.  Some of them had been broken/pulled off but the
holes were not big enough for me to enter but I could still contemplate
the dark mysteries that might have been hidden within.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3056/5696822699_4effa15765.jpg" alt="What
 lurks" /></p>

<p>The rain was fluctuating in intensity and since I was already wet I
decided to just start heading back.  For the first five or so miles I
held out the hope that the rain would stop and the sun would come back
out. After that I gave up that hope.  I was so wet that stopping to get
out of the rain would be useless. I probably would be drying if I had
jumped /into/ the Charles River. I even decided to ride /past/ home to
finish this expedition.</p>

<p>My final stop before turning to home was the Lief Erikson statue at the
beginning of the Commonwealth Avenue Mall.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5070/5696823965_8855f995d6.jpg" alt="Lief Erikson
 Statue" /></p>

<p>Having attained pictures of the statue, I hoped back into my longship
and rode it over the Harvard Bridge[11] into Cambridge and finally home.</p>

<p>The expedition, though wet, was a success.  Total ride length: 31.21
miles.  Total ride time: 3:00:22[12].</p>

<p>All pictures, in full size, of my ride are available on my <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/">flick
account</a> in <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/sets/72157626544381657/">their own
set</a>.</p>

<p>Footnotes:              <br />
[1] It appears on a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:NorthEastAmericaOrtelius1570.jpg">map dating from
1570</a></p>

<p>[2] I didn&rsquo;t know that it was the <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/Steampunk-Festival/234046964955">Steampunk
Festival</a>
in Waltham. Quite surprised to turn onto Moody street and see lots of
be-goggled folk. And Morris dancers! Who let the Morris dancers in?!</p>

<p>[3] Gale&rsquo;s chain needs replacing, it is at that stage where it will jump
off the rear cog if I am pedaling over hard bumps.  Furthermore she has
taken to shifting randomly from 1st into 2nd.</p>

<p>[4] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eben_Norton_Horsford">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eben_Norton_Horsford</a></p>

<p>[5] He was appointed to the chair in 1847.</p>

<p>[6] And, frankly, silly.</p>

<p>[7] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lief_Erikson">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lief_Erikson</a></p>

<p>[8] Thanks Wendy!</p>

<p>[9] <a href="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5064/5697393836_98b183d40f.jpg">http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5064/5697393836_98b183d40f.jpg</a></p>

<p>[10] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norumbega_Tower">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norumbega_Tower</a></p>

<p>[11] The name of &ldquo;Mass Ave. Bridge&rdquo; is &ldquo;The Harvard Bridge&rdquo;. Of course
no one calls it that since it is no were near Harvard.</p>

<p>[12] My cyclocomputer only counts time that the wheels are spinning. So
times I took a break or waited in traffic are not counted in this time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
