<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bicycle | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/bicycle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-29T15:21:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Century Ride]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/07/08/another-century-ride/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-08T20:12:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/07/08/another-century-ride</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-stats">The Stats</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Departure Time: 2012-07-08T06:11EDT</li>
  <li>Arrival Time: 2012-07-08T18:00EDT (approximately)</li>
  <li>Distance: 105.47 miles</li>
  <li>Travel Time: 10h20m</li>
  <li>Average speed: 10.42mph</li>
  <li>Total Time: ~12h</li>
  <li>Days since <a href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2011/07/11/century-ride-report-bicycle-century/">Previous Century</a>: 364 (2011-07-10)</li>
</ul>

<p>Yes, I am a very slow rider. I ride a 1971 Schwinn 3-speed. Deal with it.</p>

<h2 id="places-seen-people-met">Places Seen, People Met</h2>
<p>I traveled through a variety of cities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Boston</li>
  <li>Cambridge</li>
  <li>Arlington</li>
  <li>Bedford</li>
  <li>Concord</li>
  <li>Maynard</li>
  <li>Hudson</li>
  <li>Marlborough</li>
  <li>Southborough</li>
  <li>Hopkington</li>
  <li>Holliston</li>
  <li>Sherborn</li>
  <li>Natick</li>
  <li>Wellesley</li>
  <li>Weston</li>
  <li>Waltham</li>
  <li>Newton</li>
  <li>Watertown</li>
  <li>Maybe some more I didn’t even know I was in.</li>
</ul>

<p>I saw lovely tree-lined streets, I saw lovely tree-lined dirt-roads which
Google Maps says are bike trails, I saw empty suburban neighborhoods, I saw
strip-mall blight, I saw a wide variety.</p>

<p>I found out that while urban/suburban folk put out furniture with a ‘Free’
sign; rural folk put out yellow squash with a ‘Free’ sign.</p>

<p>I saw part of Hopkington twice; but the nice guy on the 2nd story porch
pointed me in the right direction. I told him “Hopefully you won’t see me
again” as I left, and he did not.</p>

<p>I stopped to tie my shoe and the homeowner working on his lawn asked to make
sure I had enough water - was going to get me ice-cold water if I wanted; then
we chatted about my bike and bikes he’s had.</p>

<p>I was only defeated by one hill: traveling south on Cedar St. to Hopkington
it appeared to me that the hill was about a 45 degree angle and maybe a half
mile long. After all the hills in Marlborough I decided to just walk up it.</p>

<p>I reached a personal-goal in the ride of riding across Interstate 495, I did
it twice; the second time was an overpass with no ramps was much nicer than
the first.</p>

<p>I managed to hit 30mph or come close a few times again; with a good road
surface that speed is much safer feeling. But one must be vigilant of any
possible bumps, and to be able to evade them takes a road clear of traffic.</p>

<h2 id="the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly">The Good, The Bad and the Ugly</h2>

<p>It was good to go somewhere brand new to me, it was also good to have portions
of my ride be familiar; especially the end where after reaching Norumbega
Tower I knew exactly how to get home.</p>

<p>The bad was that I started the ride with a boring loop around the Charles and
then the very familiar ride out to Concord. I found that this stretch was the
most dis-spiriting; it was just a boring ride. The rest of my ride (except the
last leg home) was new roads I had never biked on (but I had driven a car on a
few it turns out). This was all exploration - that is what I need during such
a long ride.</p>

<p>The ugly? To put it delicately: my ass hurts.</p>

<h2 id="would-i-do-it-again">Would I do it again?</h2>

<p>Of course I would - I’m just that sort of stupid.</p>

<p>I need to find places to go and things to see. I also need to make sure the
ride is as comfortable as possible.</p>

<p>Possible future rides (Century or not):</p>

<ul>
  <li>To Providence with a stop in Franklin (to visit family)</li>
  <li>To the source of the Charles River</li>
  <li>To Seebrook Power Plant</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ride Bikes Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/11/27/ride-bikes-everyday/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-27T23:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/11/27/ride-bikes-everyday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.explosm.net/db/files/Comics/Rob/gottaStudy.png" alt="Ride Bikes Everyday" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Century Ride Report ]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/07/11/century-ride-report-bicycle-century/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/07/11/century-ride-report-bicycle-century</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is what a completed century looks like:
<img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6135/5924325779_8759bf2911_d.jpg" alt="DONE" /> Everything else are just details.</p>

<p>The dramatis personae of this story are: a 40 year old male:
<img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2699/4419808164_7710801f44_d.jpg" alt="myself" /> and a 39
year-old lady
<img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5231/5901903172_fb4fbe78b7_d.jpg" alt="Gale" /></p>

<p>The trip was approximately[1] the following <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?saddr=Central+Square,+Cambridge,+MA+02139&amp;daddr=Salem,+MA+to:42.55182,-70.83646+to:Town+of+Manchester-by-the-Sea,+Manchester-by-the-Sea,+MA+to:Magnolia,+Gloucester,+MA+to:Gloucester,+MA+to:Rockport,+MA&amp;hl=en&amp;ll=42.54388,-70.87364&amp;spn=0.011066,0.022681&amp;sll=42.552132,-70.837462&amp;sspn=0.011065,0.022681&amp;geocode=FZlxhgIdFwjD-ynpwOBIUXfjiTFLx8G9sLwZUg%3BFfTLiAIdtDPG-ym3VvhqZGnjiTFFWaWlorjggQ%3BFQxKiQIdFB_H-yn72FRgbRbjiTHZHwtnQNugJw%3BFYKtiQIdqzrI-ynF6Iek4jzjiTGLmKUWhIum3w%3BFYufiQIduArJ-yk1ORclXjvjiTESuOi5ACYccw%3BFXhEigIdm8jJ-ykxAHOGgiTjiTHtwm8wq7fV6g%3BFaPfigIdXmvK-yk77KC7jSPjiTHxfw2gWoFWOQ&amp;mra=dpe&amp;mrsp=2&amp;sz=16&amp;via=2&amp;dirflg=b&amp;z=16&amp;lci=bike">route</a>.</p>

<p>The fact that it ended up being a Century was a bit of a self-trick on
my part.  I planned on the trip to Salem and <em>maybe</em> further.  Of course
when i got to Salem I felt great (only 15-20 miles) so I went off to
Manchester-by-the-sea; and still felt great so off to Gloucester etc.
Thus after 50 miles I was standing on the train platform in Rockport
looking at the sign: <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6003/5924887054_1d3a343d06_d.jpg" alt="Inbound to Boston" />
and thinking &ndash; yes, time to head back.</p>

<p>Along the way I saw some lovely sea-sides, like the dock at Rockport
where Gale posed for me <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6138/5924886428_b7d0c5681b_d.jpg" alt="Gale at the water's edge" />
and Independence Beach in Beverly: <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6025/5924319663_7555c2667e_d.jpg" alt="Left Side" />
<img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6150/5924320097_6b037ccecc_d.jpg" alt="Right Side" />
Also somewhere, I passed this lovely marsh: <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6018/5924883828_043be25cbc_d.jpg" alt="a lovely marsh" /></p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t all lovely however, the roads were not always pleasant, the
hills steep, and the pilgrims unfriendly: <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6022/5924318777_86f9b256e4_d.jpg" alt="Conant disapproves of this frivolous travel on a Sunday!" /></p>

<p>Salem,
where I took my longest stop in either direction seemed to have only one
bike rack in the center of town <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6023/5924887538_d82fa62e34_d.jpg" alt="The official Salem Bike Rack(tm)" />
The sad monuments in Gloucester made me remember the loved one I left
behind when I &ldquo;[went] down to the sea [by bike]&rdquo; <img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6127/5924884680_fe021859fb_d.jpg" alt="Loved ones left behind" />
<img src="http://farm7.static.flickr.com/6128/5924323029_f6a268ef9b_d.jpg" alt="They that go down to the sea in ships" /></p>

<p>In the end it was a great trip.  The day was lovely and I managed not to back down from the challenge. I set myself a goal of riding a century this year and have done it.  It&rsquo;s very good to know that I <strong>can</strong> set myself a goal and carry it out.  I hope to take this knowledge and remind myself of it when I hit low points in my other goals/projects.</p>

<p>=====</p>

<p>Footnotes:</p>

<p>[1] (I say approximately since I took several wrong turns here and there (more like wrong straight-ons-when-should-have-turned-s) but that luckily found a slightly nicer track right when I got into Beverly by going on Lothrop Street which led me along the water.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Viking Boston Bike Ride: The Trip to Norumbega]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/05/07/viking-boston-bike-ride-the-trip-to-norumbega/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/05/07/viking-boston-bike-ride-the-trip-to-norumbega</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Norumbega is a mythical place, a sort of place holder name for unknown
locations in the New England area[1].  Today I biked there, battling
thunderstorms, mobs of Steampunk cosplayers[2], and mechanical failures[3], to
the dark, abandoned, closed tower which is the lonely outpost of the
area&rsquo;s long lost Viking past.</p>

<p>Eben Norton Horsford[4] held the Rumford Chair of the Application of
Science to the Useful Arts at Harvard in the late 1840&rsquo;s[5].  He later
founded the Rumford Chemical Works and produced an improved recipe for
baking powder. This baking powder is still being produced as <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/5696817133/in/set-72157626544381657">Rumford
Baking
Powder</a>.
He also held the controversial[6] idea that Lief Erikson[7] sailed up
the Charles River, as far as Waltham (near present day Brandeis
University) and ultimately building a house in Cambridge.</p>

<p>I decided that I would trace Leif&rsquo;s trip up Charles River, Gale would be
my longship and we&rsquo;d brave all trials and tribulations we might find
along the way.</p>

<p>The expedition started as all good expeditions do with a good
breakfast (in this case supplied by my lovely wife Wendy who cooked some
delicious pancakes[8]), and the laying in of supplies (16oz of
Clover&trade; brewed New Guinea coffee put into my thermos from the local
Starbucks).  With these preliminaries completed I started my fateful
trip.</p>

<p>Stopping first to contemplate the location of Lief Erikson&rsquo;s house.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3119/5696817467_2579529afb.jpg" alt="Location of Lief Erikson's House" /></p>

<p>It lay just outside the back of Mt. Auburn Hospital, I wondered just
what this spot must have looked like in the year 1000 BCE; probably less
traffic.</p>

<p>From there I started the long ride up the river to my next destination.
I had not before ridden so far up the river (usually just stopping at
Watertown dam).  I took several wrong turns because I didn&rsquo;t know how
the &ldquo;Blue Heron&rdquo;[9] path ran so I missed it in a few places; and worse
turned in the wrong direction entirely when part of it turned out to be
closed in Waltham.  The clouds were rolling in and so was the thunder, I
was worried that I was going to be caught in the rain and I had not yet
found the tower. Riding through Mt. Feake Cemetery the rain caught up
with me.  Through the cemetery quickly and then ducking into the
Brandeis-Roberts train stop I hoped to wait out the rain.  I sipped some
coffee and waited.  The rain continued but it looked like it was
brightening.  Checking my map I knew I was close to the tower.  I
decided that the rain was lightening up so I recounted for the final
stretch.</p>

<p>Mother Nature, that fickle woman, was up to her usual tricks and mere
moments later I was soaked as the rain quickly got worse.  I pressed on
to the tower and was pleasantly surprised to find it much easier to find
than expected.</p>

<p>The tower marks the location where there had been a Norse
fort/city[10] according to Horsford.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2756/5697394164_817d1d3379.jpg" alt="Norumbega
 Tower" /></p>

<p>At one point it seemed that the public could climb the inside of the
tower to enjoy the view from the top, but now it was all blocked off
with welded in gates.  Some of them had been broken/pulled off but the
holes were not big enough for me to enter but I could still contemplate
the dark mysteries that might have been hidden within.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3056/5696822699_4effa15765.jpg" alt="What
 lurks" /></p>

<p>The rain was fluctuating in intensity and since I was already wet I
decided to just start heading back.  For the first five or so miles I
held out the hope that the rain would stop and the sun would come back
out. After that I gave up that hope.  I was so wet that stopping to get
out of the rain would be useless. I probably would be drying if I had
jumped /into/ the Charles River. I even decided to ride /past/ home to
finish this expedition.</p>

<p>My final stop before turning to home was the Lief Erikson statue at the
beginning of the Commonwealth Avenue Mall.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5070/5696823965_8855f995d6.jpg" alt="Lief Erikson
 Statue" /></p>

<p>Having attained pictures of the statue, I hoped back into my longship
and rode it over the Harvard Bridge[11] into Cambridge and finally home.</p>

<p>The expedition, though wet, was a success.  Total ride length: 31.21
miles.  Total ride time: 3:00:22[12].</p>

<p>All pictures, in full size, of my ride are available on my <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/">flick
account</a> in <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/verdammelt/sets/72157626544381657/">their own
set</a>.</p>

<p>Footnotes:              <br />
[1] It appears on a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:NorthEastAmericaOrtelius1570.jpg">map dating from
1570</a></p>

<p>[2] I didn&rsquo;t know that it was the <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/Steampunk-Festival/234046964955">Steampunk
Festival</a>
in Waltham. Quite surprised to turn onto Moody street and see lots of
be-goggled folk. And Morris dancers! Who let the Morris dancers in?!</p>

<p>[3] Gale&rsquo;s chain needs replacing, it is at that stage where it will jump
off the rear cog if I am pedaling over hard bumps.  Furthermore she has
taken to shifting randomly from 1st into 2nd.</p>

<p>[4] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eben_Norton_Horsford">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eben_Norton_Horsford</a></p>

<p>[5] He was appointed to the chair in 1847.</p>

<p>[6] And, frankly, silly.</p>

<p>[7] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lief_Erikson">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lief_Erikson</a></p>

<p>[8] Thanks Wendy!</p>

<p>[9] <a href="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5064/5697393836_98b183d40f.jpg">http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5064/5697393836_98b183d40f.jpg</a></p>

<p>[10] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norumbega_Tower">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norumbega_Tower</a></p>

<p>[11] The name of &ldquo;Mass Ave. Bridge&rdquo; is &ldquo;The Harvard Bridge&rdquo;. Of course
no one calls it that since it is no were near Harvard.</p>

<p>[12] My cyclocomputer only counts time that the wheels are spinning. So
times I took a break or waited in traffic are not counted in this time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rode a 1/3 century!]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/02/rode-a-13-century/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2011/04/02/rode-a-13-century</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My goal today was to ride a &ldquo;marathon&rdquo; &ndash; but in the end I extended
myself to 1/3 century.  Given that I had some errands to run I just made
that the &ldquo;reason&rdquo; for my trip.  I rode Gale. <img title="My lovely steed" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3506/3181434926_a4748e5e20_d.jpg" alt="Gale" />  Gale is a 39 year old, many-10s of pounds 3
speed. She&rsquo;s awesome. </p>

<p>First to get fitted for a tux &ndash; that was easy &ndash; but I realized that my
bike computer wasn&rsquo;t zeroed out so I did that when I got to the mall &ndash;
so 2.5-3 miles is actually missing from the rest of this story.</p>

<p>Then to the vet &ndash; over the hills of Brookline &ndash; to get cat food.  Ugh
the hills killed my knees because I took them too aggressively.  The 8lb
bag made the bike a bit wobbly &ndash; but made it home OK.</p>

<p>Then I rode off to the office to load up both panniers with books from
the office &ndash; no reason to leave the books there anymore.  Two panniers
FULL of compsci books made the bike VERY wiggly, had to be very
careful. A protest in the common right where I get into it diverted me
around the common on the street &ndash; which gave me the opportunity to see
and say Hi to a coworker, Heather Kanser.</p>

<p>Now, home again, I had to go back out to get mileage.  I decided to head
to Fresh Pond and take a ride around.  Lovely ride but the clouds were
gathering and then the &ldquo;lovely&rdquo; spring rain started.  Cold but
refreshing.  The path around the reservoir was annoying &ndash; LOTS of dog
walking &ndash; will need to check if bicycles are even allowed on the path &ndash;
maybe not.</p>

<p>It was on the way back that I got to my first goal, a marathon of
riding: <img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5180/5583426508_674c3241d6_m_d.jpg" alt="A marathon of
riding" />
and I decided to push on to 1/3 century &ndash; but where to go? Why the
Squirrel Brand Company building: <img title="The place where delicious candy was developed" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5299/5582840175_54992eeb9a_d.jpg" alt="Squirrel Brand
Company" />.  Heading towards home
I realized I needed to pad my ride a bit more &ndash; so I just took a LONG
way home &ndash; and riding through a COLD rain &ndash; and then finally: <img title="Made it!" src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5025/5582840443_237d7fa63d_m_d.jpg" alt="33.33
miles" />.</p>

<p>Got home a very short ride later and my final ride was just a bit over
1/3 century <img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5259/5583427320_111cfc35c7_m_d.jpg" alt="Final
Tally" />.
Average speed just over 10mph. </p>

<p>Other than my knees bothering me a bit (due to the overly aggressive
early riding) I&rsquo;m feeling good.  Going to go get some Chinese food!</p>

<p>LoseIt helpfully tells me that my ride burned 1424 calories.  Means I
can eat plenty of it without worry.  Yum.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
