<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: listening | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/listening/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T09:01:10-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Having a conversation with your code]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/09/having-a-conversation-with-your-code/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T10:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/09/having-a-conversation-with-your-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just sat in on a talk by Cory Foy entitled “When Code Cries: Listening to What
Your Code is Saying”.</p>

<p>(Warning: there will be anthropomorphizing of source code in this post)</p>

<p>One thing I wanted to pull out of it is the idea of <em>listening</em> to your code.
Really listening. Like it was a person.</p>

<p>I don’t think it is just listening to code - but a conversation with code. The
programmer is talking about what they need, and the code is telling the
programmer what it needs. It is a give and take like any conversation. If one
side of the conversation tries to dominate, or ignores the other, the outcome
will not be successful. Like any conversation the failure may not be immediate
but later when misunderstandings between the parties of the conversation cause
problems.</p>

<p>Listening is not easy however. To really listen you have to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Decide to listen</li>
  <li>Listen for the whole message</li>
  <li>Let go of your personal agenda</li>
  <li>Be patient</li>
  <li>Be curious</li>
  <li>Test for understanding</li>
</ul>

<p>I personally have problems with listening patiently for the whole message.  I
tend to jump in, trying to add things, perhaps of my own agenda, saying things
starting with “So what you’re saying is…” instead of just waiting to find
out what is being said. With code this comes out when I too quickly jump to
refactorings or thinking that my coding task is done - because I’m not
listening to the code.</p>

<p>Having a conversation with code is not easy either. Mike Clement
<a href="https://twitter.com/mdclement">@mdclement</a> likened it to talking with his 18
month old child. They can’t talk - but they are trying to communicate. One
needs to be patient in order to get the message.</p>

<p>I am working on being a better listener, with people, but I can see that I
need to work on those skills for my code as well.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
