<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cube | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/cube/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-03-02T10:47:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Year Without a Office Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/04/08/a-year-without-a-office-desk/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-08T20:09:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/04/08/a-year-without-a-office-desk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Well not quite true I don’t have a desk at all… but effectively I don’t
have one).</p>

<p>About a year ago I changed to a new job. In all previous jobs I’ve had I had a
desk, in fact I had a office (sometimes shared) or at least a cube of my own.
It was different at the new job; when I showed up on my first day at the new
work there was a little bit of confusion about what cube I could be given and
as a ‘temporary’ solution I was given a desk in the lab.</p>

<p>Given the way we work on the team, I spent very little time at my desk. It
became simply a place where I put my bag &amp; coat; a place for my coffee mug; a
place for my notebook at the end of the day. I did use it to check my email
first thing in the morning before everyone arrived (I’m an early person) - but
other than that - unused. As the months went on I used it less and less
everyday.</p>

<p>Then in January the new DBA consultant started sitting at it with his laptop
so he could be with the team; thus I was partially evicted from my ‘desk’. I
still kept my inbox there - but now I didn’t even use the desk to read my
email in the morning.</p>

<p>At this same time there was a new coworker starting and with that a little
angst about where they would sit (the cube situation was in fact no better;
but actually worse). A cube was found for her; but I felt that by giving up my
desk entirely I was making a personal statement about desks, cubes, offices.</p>

<p>I do have regrets periodically when I need to do some personal matters; but we
have a shared office nearby the lab and a few cubes that can be used in a
pinch for private work/calls.</p>

<p>In all - I have not really missed having a desk. I have found out that I don’t
need much more than space for my inbox; maybe someday space for some filing.
This conclusion is NOT what I would have expected from myself; I remember
clearly wanting an office and bemoaning my fate of being in cubes. It seems I
have accepted the team-room setting more than I had imagined I could have.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
