<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cocktail | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/cocktail/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T10:10:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to stock a bar]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2013/03/11/how-to-stock-a-bar/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-11T22:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2013/03/11/how-to-stock-a-bar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>
<p>As everyone that knows me knows, I have become enamored with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocktail">cocktails</a>.</p>

<p>So I thought, with that amazing hubris encapsulated within the novice, I would
tell you, the reader, how to stock a bar if you are new to cocktails yourself.</p>

<p>I’ll split this amateur’s amateur guide into the following sections:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The Equipment</li>
  <li>The Drink</li>
  <li>The Practice</li>
  <li>The Expansion</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="the-equipment">The Equipment</h1>

<p>I will start by listing the equipment you need. This will seem like a lot; but
you can find some of it in ‘kits’ which will help you get started (replacing
crappy items as you realize that there are better tools).</p>

<ul>
  <li>a jigger<sup id="fnref:jigger"><a href="#fn:jigger" class="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>a shaker set. (I prefer a Boston Shaker<sup id="fnref:bostonshaker"><a href="#fn:bostonshaker" class="footnote">2</a></sup>)</li>
  <li>a strainer (such as a Hawthorne Strainer<sup id="fnref:strainer"><a href="#fn:strainer" class="footnote">3</a></sup>)</li>
  <li>a bar spoon<sup id="fnref:barspoon"><a href="#fn:barspoon" class="footnote">4</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<p>This seems like a lot of stuff - but like I said you can find it in ‘kits’. If
you can get better tools from a specialty store (such as <a href="http://www.thebostonshaker.com/">The Boston Shaker</a>).</p>

<h1 id="the-drink">The Drink</h1>

<p>You should start with one or two drinks you like and that have only a few
ingredients. For example a Manhattan or Negroni only have 3 ingredients; a Gin
and Tonic only two (three if you count the lime). Pick drinks you really like
because you will be making them a lot.  It also helps if you pick drinks with
‘standard’ ingredients, like Gin, Vodka, Rye, Bourbon, Whisky, Campari etc.
This makes it easier to buy these ingredients from your local liquor store.</p>

<h1 id="the-practice">The Practice</h1>

<p>Now that you have the equipment and the ingredients; make yourself a drink –
you deserve it! Then make it again, and again, and again…</p>

<p>As you practice, you’ll figure out how to measure (and when you don’t care
about measuring), you’ll figure out how to stir or shake well, how much ice
you might need etc.</p>

<h1 id="the-expansion">The Expansion</h1>

<p>Once you have gotten good a drink (or perhaps sick of it) look for a drink
which has all the same ingredients but in different proportions; or a drink
that has a different ingredient you don’t have yet.</p>

<p>In this way your repertoire will grow and your skill will as well.</p>

<hr />
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:jigger">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jigger_(unit)#Jigger <a href="#fnref:jigger" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:bostonshaker">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_shaker <a href="#fnref:bostonshaker" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:strainer">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocktail_strainer <a href="#fnref:strainer" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:barspoon">
      <p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bar_spoon <a href="#fnref:barspoon" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cocktail: Bijou]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/23/cocktail-bijou/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-23T16:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/23/cocktail-bijou</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I visited <a href="https://twitter.com/BrickMortarLtd">Brick and Mortar</a> before Thanksgiving for a Sazerac
and to let Lisa know that I’d be in on Monday with the
<a href="https://twitter.com/codeandcocktail">Code-and-Cocktails</a> group. She pointed to a cocktail on
their menu she thought I might like.  <a href="https://twitter.com/hankyp">Misty</a> came over after my
Sazerac was done and I ordered it; since it had [Chartreuse][chartreuse] in it
I decided to ask her what the differences, if any, there were between Green
and Yellow Chartreuse. Turns out there are a bunch of differences and Misty
was quite happy to tell me about them. I asked if I could have a taste of each
to compare and she obliged.</p>

<p>I’m bad at describing tastes but I can say that Yellow Chartreuse is sweeter
and not as strong, the Green is a stronger Liqueur and not as sweet, more
herbal.</p>

<p>After this experiment I decided I needed to get some and add more drinks to my
home repertoire. After buying it I pinged Misty on twitter and asked for a
recommendation for a drink combining gin, or rye, or vermouth (my staples)
with the Chartreuse. She pointed me at the Bijou. The recipe she gave me was:
equal parts gin, chartreuse and sweet vermouth (I did 1oz), a dash of orange
bitters and lemon oil garnishing.</p>

<p>The taste was very complicated and very good. Chartreuse is something I am
going to continue to explore.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Palm Beach Special]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/07/26/the-palm-beach-special/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T19:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/07/26/the-palm-beach-special</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(It was noted to me that for a blog called ‘code and cocktails’ that I
don’t have many cocktail related posts - so here we go:)</p>

<p>I decided to try a new-to-me cocktail tonight and asked
<a href="http://cocktaildb.com/">cocktaildb</a> for cocktails which contain grapefruit and gin.  It suggested,
amongst others, the <a href="http://cocktaildb.com/recipe_detail?id=4758">Palm Beach Special</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>2 1/2 oz. gin</li>
  <li>3/4 oz. grapefruit juice</li>
  <li>1/2 oz. sweet vermouth</li>
  <li>shake well with ice, strain into cocktail glass.</li>
</ul>

<p>I enjoy the combination of gin and grapefruit in this drink but I have two
issues with it which I’d like to experiment with:</p>

<ol>
  <li>I think it is too heavy on the gin - I think it overloads the grapefruit.</li>
  <li>I wonder if something like St. Germaine might be a good exchange for sweet
vermouth - obviously it would change the drink - but I think it might be
for the better.</li>
</ol>

<p>As an aside: cocktaildb is a great resource - I wish I could filter out drinks
for which I don’t have ingredients however.  That is why I am building
(slowly) my own cocktail recipe website <a href="http://defdrink.heroku.com"><code>(defdrink)</code></a>. (The primary
purpose of <code>(defdrink)</code> is to be a vehicle for me to learn <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a>)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lotus Eaters]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/05/15/the-lotus-eaters/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-15T20:14:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/05/15/the-lotus-eaters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odyssey">Odyssey</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…but gave them to eat of the lotus, which was so delicious that those
   who ate of it left off caring about home</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I believe that the <a href="sazerac">Sazerac</a> may be my ‘lotus’ - what is yours?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code'n'Cocktails - crazy idea?]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/01/15/coden-cocktails-crazy-idea/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-15T19:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/01/15/coden-cocktails-crazy-idea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I jokingly I mentioned the idea of Code’n’Cocktails on Twitter…</p>

<p>https://twitter.com/#!/verdammelt/status/158292007981289472</p>

<p>This was shortly after a short conversation while partaking of aprés
<a href="http://groups.google.com/group/boston-software-craftsmanship?pli=1">Boston Software Craftsmanship</a> beers in which I was asked about
cocktails and someone suggested getting cocktails after the meeting next time.
It was also immediately after I was asked when we were going to get cocktails
by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/zdsbs">@zdsbs</a> (prompted by my tweeting I had just purchased <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Absinthe-Cocktails-Green-Fairy-ebook/dp/B006L63108">a book of
Absinthe Cocktail recipes</a>).</p>

<p>I did but jest (<em>poison in jest; no offense i’the world</em> [Hamlet
III.ii.234-235])…</p>

<p>But now I am thinking it through.</p>

<p>I have heard of <a href="http://www.meetup.com/london-software-craftsmanship/events/48227772/">‘Code &amp; Coffee’</a>
and thought it a good idea.  A place to meet people who like code and coffee.
While I <strong>really</strong> like coffee, I also like cocktails and I seem to be
surrounded by people who get up later than I do - so why not meet <em>after</em> work
for cocktails and code?  <em>Brilliant!</em></p>

<p>So what would a Code’n’Cocktail look like?  I see a few possibilities:</p>

<ol>
  <li>A cocktail party where code/coding is the topic of conversation</li>
  <li>A coding dojo/coderetreat/code kata session with booze</li>
  <li>A <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salon_(gathering)"><em>salon</em></a> for
coding</li>
</ol>

<p>I think the first and last are very similar and given my inclinations I like
the connotations of referring to it as a <em>salon</em>.  I think that would be my
preference.  I would not want to limit it entirely to discussion; so some
coding would be good.</p>

<p>What do I hope attendees would get out of such an event?  I think attendees
should have fun and at least one of: learn something, teach something, make
contacts.</p>

<p>This sort of event would have to happen at a bar or someone’s home.  I don’t
see how it could happen at someone’s workplace or a place like <a href="http://microsoftcambridge.com/Default.aspx">NERD</a> as it
<strong>obviously</strong> needs a well stocked bar.  The problem is location.  The
Location would need to be able to accommodate an prior-to-event unknown number
of people (making a reservation would be difficult); and accommodate the
possibility of coding (standing at a bar may not work).  I think an off night
at a bar might work - the place would love to get business on a slow night…</p>

<p>The gears in my mind are turning.  If you have interest or thoughts please
comment or contact me.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
