<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coderetreat | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/coderetreat/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-13T21:22:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coderetreat - the need for preparedness]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2011/12/04/coderetreat-the-need-for-preparedness/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2011/12/04/coderetreat-the-need-for-preparedness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Abstract</h2>

<p>This observer has noted a repeated waste of time by attendees of the
<a href="http://coderetreat.org/">Coderetreats</a> he has attended. Herein is described a
simple way to be better prepared when you attend your next Coderetreat</p>

<h2>Observational Data</h2>

<p>This past weekend was the Global Day of Coderetreat and I attended the
one in <a href="http://coderetreat.org/events/global-day-of-coderetreat">Cambridge, Mass</a>. This was my third and I
again saw an annoyance I want to get out of my head.</p>

<p>First, let me recapitulate the idea of the code retreat.  The
participants work on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conways_Game_of_Life">Conway&rsquo;s Game of Life</a> programming
problem in 45 minute intervals in pairs, throwing away the code after
every iteration.  Some iterations have interesting constraints added;
such as &lsquo;no primitives&rsquo;, &lsquo;no ifs&rsquo;, or &lsquo;silent paring&rsquo;.</p>

<p>I have noticed that at each coderetreat I&rsquo;ve attended some people spend
time (usually only in the first session luckily) fighting with their
environments to get the point where they can start coding. To me any
time spent setting up the environment is wasted time when you have 45
minutes.  I&rsquo;m not saying that this was a /huge/ issue &ndash; but a very
little bit of preparation can save plenty of time during the event.</p>

<h2>An Initial Attempt for a Personal Solution</h2>

<p>Given that I saw (and felt, when pairing with someone who was
unprepared) this problem at the Chicago coderetreat (held the day after
<a href="http://scna.softwarecraftsmanship.org/">SCNA</a>), I made sure I had a ruby and Java project all set up so
that I had a failing test (<code>true == false</code>).  That way I knew that
everything was all set: all needed libraries, any special configuration
(<a href="http://www.zenspider.com/ZSS/Products/ZenTest/">autotest</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.relishapp.com/rspec">rspec</a> always gives me a little bit of
hassle), any other annoying little thing was done.  I even went so far
as to push them up to <a href="https://.github.com">GitHub</a> so others could use them to.
(git makes deleting the code after an iteration very easy: <code>git reset
--hard HEAD &amp;&amp; git clean -fqx</code>).</p>

<p>It turns out that I didn&rsquo;t need to do this.  There was already a GitHub
repository that did what I needed and much more:
<a href="https://github.com/coreyhaines/coderetreat">coreyhaines/coderetreat</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Given that the above repository is set up for 10 programming languages
currently, it is likely that the ones you want to use are already
there.  Simply cloning the repository and doing a quick smoke test will
ensure that your environment is ready for the session.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t find your favorite language &ndash; or the skeleton provided
doesn&rsquo;t work as well as it could &ndash; send a pull request (I tweaked the
ruby starting point to let autotest work with rspec right away).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#coderetreat thoughts]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2010/10/19/coderetreat-thoughts/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2010/10/19/coderetreat-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The code retreat at the 8th Light offices was the first one I had ever <br />attended. Overall I thought it was great, and again was well organized <br />like the SCNA conference was. <p /> I came into the code retreat feeling a bit intimidated and left feeling <br />tired and a bit intimidated. Just like the conference the code retreat <br />was _tiring_, but still a good tired. And like the conference I was a <br />bit intimidated by all the passionate, smart people around me. I hope <br />to be half as good as these people are. <p /> I am very happy that I did get to pair with really smart people in <br />Clojure, Ruby, Javascript and C#. <p /> * High Points: <p /> ** I had never written a line of Javascript before and never even really <br /> read much either. It is very weird, but in a good way. I'm going to <br /> add it to my list in order to at least familiarize myself with it. I <br /> think knowing a bit of it will help me understand other languages <br /> better. My pair (Sean McMillan) did a very good job taking the time to explain the <br /> features and constructs of the language so that we can work <br /> together.<p /> ** The God class was an accident, as most gods are probably. Marty and <br /> I started the session saying we'd work on the 'always delegate' <br /> constraint. We quickly decided that Cells needed to delegate to <br /> someone above them... who could that be? God of course. But that <br /> flippant naming changed EVERYTHING. The whole session changed. All <br /> our naming changed. Near the end, we were writing some code and it <br /> wasn't feeling right, Corey pointed out the encapsulation problem in <br /> it. Cells were telling God what to do. Nothing can tell God what to <br /> do! The problem would have been visible without the naming but with <br /> the naming the code FELT wrong. <p /> ** During lunch we had a discussion that brought up the idea of the <br /> Cells themselves knowing about their neighbors, mixing this with <br /> genetic programming could lead to extra data on each cell which gets <br /> combined when the dead cell comes back to life rule is applied, as <br /> this could be seen as a reproductive step. Furthermore the extra <br /> data could be somehow relevant to the Game of Life itself, e.g. some <br /> cells might be more resistant to over/under-population than others, <br /> thus surviving longer. I found this a very interesting idea and may <br /> try to find time to play with it more. <p /> * Low Points: <p /> I felt I was a bad pair in a few cases as my thinking got rather cloudy <br />and unfocused at a few points in the afternoon (especially when pairing <br />in C# with @MaggieLongshore! sorry!) <p /> * In Retrospect: In retrospect I feel I could have gotten more out of it if I could have <br />snapped myself out of my mindset that I wanted to "get as far as I <br />could" earlier in the day. That would have let me play with other <br />constraints, like no numbers, totally functional etc. <p /> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
