<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bugs | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/bugs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-03-02T10:47:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[To Estimating Bugs or Not: The Definitive Answer]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/08/03/estimating-bugs/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T16:31:11-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/08/03/estimating-bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was recently re-reading the XP books and in <em>Extreme Programming
Installed</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup> I came upon a section where the authors say that bugs
should be estimated and planned into iterations like other stories.
I disagreed with that idea, thinking about how ‘<em>opinion had changed</em>’
on that topic since the book was written and that ‘<em>that’s not how I
was taught to do it</em>’.</p>

<p>Then I wondered <em>why</em> I thought that, just who had taught me that bugs
should not be estimated. At first I assumed it was Jim Shore from <em>The
Art of Agile</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>, but a quick look in the book<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote">3</a></sup> shows that he says
<em>to</em> estimate bug stories. That led me to do some looking around the
Internet<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote">4</a></sup> and discuss this issue with my colleagues at Cyrus
Innovation<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote">5</a></sup>.</p>

<p>I know believe I have the definitive answer to the question of whether
or not to estimate bugs.</p>

<p>(First a clarification: I am not talking about defects found during an
iteration in, or caused by, stories being worked on during that
iteration. That just means that story is not done. Don’t take credit
for it and create a bug card. Just accept that the story is not done.)</p>

<p>And now for that definitive answer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>It depends.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Some teams might find it useful to give the Customer the ability to
prioritize bugs along with other work. By estimating the bugs the
Customer has all the data they need to make their trade-offs. That
being said: estimating bugs can be very difficult since there is often
more than the usual share of unknown unknowns; thus the estimate will
be less reliable than normal.</p>

<p>Some teams might find it useful to estimate bugs so that planning an
iteration is easier. If a team knows it can do 14 points of work, then
14 points of work can be taken off the top of the backlog, maybe they
are all bugs, or some bugs or no bugs; doesn’t matter - it is 14
points. If bugs are not estimated then maybe the team can do some bugs
and how many more points? <em>shrug</em>.</p>

<p>Some teams might find that estimating bugs allows the number of bugs
to be hidden among the work being done. They want to make sure that
bugs are always visible, so they do <em>not</em> estimate want to make sure
that bugs always detract from their velocity. Estimating bugs makes
them a bit more <em>normal</em> and thus less visible.</p>

<p>So ultimately, as with any such question, the answer depends upon the
needs and desires of the team. Do what works for you, and periodically
question why and even try a different way.</p>

<p>(Drink Pairing: I paired the writing of this post with a simple
Daiquiri<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote">6</a></sup>.)</p>

<hr />
<p>and strain.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>http://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Installed-Ron-Jeffries/dp/0201708426/ <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>http://www.jamesshore.com/Agile-Book/ <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>My copy contains the note: “To Mark - Here’s to sucking less! Jim Shore” <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Specifically the World Wide Web section of the Internet. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>http://www.cyrusinnovation.com/ <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>1.5oz Rum, .75oz Lime Juice, .25oz Simple Syrup. Shake over ice <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
