<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T08:38:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I have (re)-learned from SICP]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2014/07/06/what-i-have-re-learned-from-sicp/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-06T14:14:33-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2014/07/06/what-i-have-re-learned-from-sicp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After about two years of slowly working through Structure and
Interpretation of Computer Programs (SICP)<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup> I finally completed it.
I didn’t do every exercise but I did many of them<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="the-history">The History</h2>

<p>I first worked through SICP back in 1989 as part of my class at
Worcester Polytechnic Institute (where I received my BSCS in 1992). It
is a book that I remember with awe. I remember being, along with most
of the class, mystified by this <em>dumb</em> language Scheme. It was so
unlike anything we were used to. I was familiar with BASIC and Pascal
and some very basic Bourne Shell scripting. Scheme was <em>alien</em>. Most
of us thought it crazy. But then, somewhere about half-way through the
class it clicked, suddenly I <em>got it</em>. Scheme, and Lisp by
association, was amazing. The REPL development, the flexibility, the
lack and regularity of syntax gave it great power. And then… then…
we started on the chapter about the Meta-circular Evaluator<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote">3</a></sup>;
writing an evaluator of Scheme in Scheme. It was so simple, so
clear<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<p>This was a Freshman class, and the rest of my time at WPI I played
around with Lisp, sometimes doing assignments in it, playing with my
Emacs initialization files, that sort of thing. Never got serious. And
then I joined the work force in 1990 with a summer job doing C/Motif
work at a startup. And then after college a C job connecting their
Windows app to a particular printer for graphs, and then a C/Motif job
on a news ticker for a stock market application. Oh and then I
learned<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote">5</a></sup> object-oriented programming with C++… I forgot the
lessons I learned in SICP.</p>

<h2 id="the-return">The Return</h2>

<p>I went back to SICP expecting to be <em>reminded</em> of a few things. What I
found was that I was <em>taught</em> things I never remember being taught.
Things which I so wish I had grokked at the time. Things which I
obviously never understood and then forgot.</p>

<p>A few of the things I learned way back when and then forgot were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Judge a programming language by the means of abstraction and the
means of composition.</li>
  <li>The power/utility of REPL development.</li>
  <li>Lazy streams to deal with infinities are not scary.</li>
  <li>Functional Programming.</li>
  <li>Object-Oriented Programming.</li>
  <li>The Problem of State.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-reaction">The Reaction</h2>

<p>This is a <em>Freshman</em> level textbook, and all of this was taught as
early as the mid-eighties. Looking back I feel like I was caught up in
a great forgetting. There are things we (as Software Engineers<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote">6</a></sup>)
<em>knew</em> and then forgot, or chose to forget/overlook.</p>

<p>Now I see people going back to old papers/books and
re-learning/discovering what we already knew but forgot/ignored. It is
like a wider version of Greenspun’s tenth rule<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote">7</a></sup>. We had something
and then had to put it aside because it didn’t work in our
“<em>reality</em>”, but now we come back and “<em>discover</em>” it all over again.</p>

<p><strong>OMG</strong> Garbage Collection<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote">8</a></sup> <strong>OMG</strong> <em>interactive</em> language shells
(aka REPL) <strong>OMG</strong> dynamic languages <strong>OMG</strong> functional programming
<strong>OMG</strong> <em>OO</em> is about message passing.</p>

<p>What happened, were we asleep?</p>

<p>It would be one thing if we acted like these are in fact old ideas
that are just now realizing are good/possible - but we act like they
are <em>new</em>. Reality has caught up to where the 1960’s thought was
possible<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote">9</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="the-back-to-the-future">The Back to the Future</h2>

<p>One last thing I (re)learned: The fun of learning and working through
problems. And that leads to what is yet to come.</p>

<p>I’m going to start looking at the old texts of our practice. The
ancients knew things that we have forgotten. I will see what I can
learn from them. I will strive to avoid Argument from Antiquity
however, that is always a danger with this sort of thing.</p>

<p>I can only see so far because I stand upon the shoulders of Giants<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote">10</a></sup>.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/ <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>https://github.com/verdammelt/sicp <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-26.html#%_sec_4.1 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>It was in this class I created the joke idea of ‘God code’. The
  stereotypical 3 line Lisp code, first line defines function,
  second like is a null check, third line recurses. And <em>shit</em> got
  done. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p><em>“</em>learned<em>”</em> <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>Software Engineer, Programmer, Coder, Hacker whatever you want
  to call us/ourselves. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>“Any sufficiently complicated C or FORTRAN program contains an
  ad hoc, informally-specified, bug-ridden, slow implementation of
  half of Common Lisp.” <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8">
      <p>http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-33.html#%_sec_5.3 <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9">
      <p>http://www-formal.stanford.edu/jmc/recursive.pdf <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:10">
      <p>with apologies to Newton. <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Review of 20 years of 'Professional' programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/06/20/quick-review-of-20-years-of-professional-programming/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-20T21:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/06/20/quick-review-of-20-years-of-professional-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In May 1992 I graduated with a Bachelor of Science in Computer Science from
<a href="http://www.wpi.edu/" title="My alma mater">WPI</a>. That means that I’ve been a ‘<em>professional</em>’ programmer for a little
bit over 20 years.  I have to say that while on the whole it has been good I
regret some things.</p>

<p>Firstly, I think I got a good education from WPI.  However I wish I had taken
it onto myself to get a <em>better</em> education.  I didn’t extend myself enough, I
didn’t really dig into things as much as I could have. I got good grades and
left it at that.  This is a regret of mine.</p>

<p>Nextly, upon graduating, I got some jobs and things went well. I fell into
thinking that I knew what I was doing.  I think I was, while cocksure, still a
bit better than the average programmer of the time with equal experience.  But
it was during this approximately 10-15 year period where I fell into a lull. I
thought I was good and I never did too much extra-curricular research. I did
have a small piece of <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/tnef/">free software</a> that I worked on during this time</p>
<ul>
  <li>but that didn’t really stretch my abilities. The work I was doing at work
was good - but again not stretching my abilities.</li>
</ul>

<p>During this time I only remember going to a single ‘conference’. That was when
the local <a href="http://www.acm.org">ACM</a> chapter in <a href="http://www.gbcacm.org/">Boston</a> brought in one of the 
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gang_of_Four_(software)">Gang of Four</a> to talk about their book. I distinctly remember that during the
lunch I was so shy/awkward that I felt like never attending anything like this
again.</p>

<p>Sometime during the last 5-10 years I started to become dissatisfied with how
software projects were being run and how quality, my own and other developers
was being handled.  Sometime during this time period I was exposed to Agile
methodologies. Perhaps the time was just ‘right’, but for whatever reason
instead of just sitting around and accepting things I did a lot of research, I
started reading blogs, I started trying things out for myself, I even went to
conferences and made some good connections with people.</p>

<p>It was at this point I started to realized 1) how little I knew and 2) how
much I had forgotten.</p>

<p>This is where I am now. I am trying to turn myself around and learn more and
all the time.</p>

<p>I hope my next 20 years of programming (because I plan on coding (maybe not
always for pay) until I die) will not find myself falling into another rut…</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
