<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quality | Code And Cocktails]]></title>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/categories/quality/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-21T10:10:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Simpson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delivery vs. Code Quality: Any Corners Safe To Cut?]]></title>
    <link href="http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/13/delivery-vs-code-quality-any-corners-safe-to-cut/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T20:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://code-and-cocktails.heroku.com/blog/2012/11/13/delivery-vs-code-quality-any-corners-safe-to-cut</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The balancing act between delivering vs. code quality has been on my mind
lately. It seems to me that there are times when delivery trumps code quality.
But sacrificing code quality for delivery speed results in slower delivery of
future features.</p>

<p>(‘Code Quality’ here is defined as ‘good design’, ‘easy to change’, ‘easy to
understand’. This is not about quality as in free-of-bugs: that is <strong>not</strong> a
corner I will cut. I am also not suggesting writing <em>shit</em>.)</p>

<p>Are there any corners which are <em>safe</em> to cut? I have a feeling there is no
good answer; but is there a <em>right</em> answer?</p>

<p>I suppose as a bottom line the best to do is to keep the corner-cutting
explicit and visible to all people involved (that includes non-developers) so
that the eventual slowdown will not be a surprise.</p>

<p>Or is this just an invalid assumption on my part? Is there any time that
delivery can trump code quality? I know that everyone says that keeping code
quality high is the only way to go quickly
(<a href="http://twitter.com/unclebobmartin">@unclebob’s</a> pithy: “The only way to go
fast is to go well”). But that seems to be to be about the long term; I am
talking about short term speed gains.</p>

<p>This is something I’m going to continue to think about; I’d love to hear your
thoughts on this.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
